First of all, I would like to thank Jasmine this morning
[music]
she works very hard her team
all year to prepare this
event for us and without her we would not have
this program let the
team stick your
team Jasmine please stand up
and your hands
volunteers please stand up
[music]
all volunteers
[applause]
and I would like to thank
from the American side we have Team
and Reverend Jit we thank them for
organizing
[music]
we will be together for eight days I
know many of you came from far away
thank you for coming I know it's hard to find
time to come here
it's expensive to travel and stay
here and I am very grateful that you
came
[applause]
in this program in Thailand
Jasmine had a great idea she
said let's ask the students to
bring their parents and their children
so that people can have such a dorama vacation with their
families this is a very beautiful idea it
seems to me that later in our lives this is just the
time that we will remember
that we spent with our parents I am
very  I am grateful that Asmin has already come up with
such an idea that parents please stand up
thank you
[applause]
[music]
[applause] [
applause]
and where are the children the children have also arrived they are everywhere
let's applaud the children too
[music]
[applause]
and
[music]
and the programs today and every day
I will teach in the morning in frames for a
half hour usually I taught
three or four times a day and in the afternoon after
lunch everyone gets sleepy so I
decided I will conduct long classes in
the morning you are fresh I am fresh so we will have a
long class and the morning is a good
time for meditation but we will have a
long break in the morning during the morning
class so don't worry and we are not
used to sitting for so long this morning
you are still fresh but in three days you
will be tired just be strong
this is very important you will not receive these
teachings there is no other place
this teaching will help you in your life throughout your
life and also this teaching
will help you after death
so this teaching is different from all
other teachings and this is a very important time
for us in  Some days you will be
tired, some days you may have
problems in the room,
some days you will miss your
refrigerator at home, just
relax,
funk, nut, relax and listen,
open your heart.
We just returned from a special
program in Shenzhen, China, it is for
special entrepreneurs and businessmen, and
12 of them are Diaz people, of whom are here,
I would like to thank
[applause]
they study deep ideas that
can be used in business, using in the
family, so my hope is that in this
program, ours, I don’t feel that this is
some kind of religious program. We
have people from Mexico,
many people from Ukraine, Russia,
Germany, and every country has its own
culture.
Every country has its own religion.
People in Mexico, for example, have a wedding
in a church. People in Ukraine will have a
wedding in a Christian church,
and each of us has this family culture,
and we must respect this
culture.
[music]
people in Mexico do not want to have a
wedding.  a ceremony in a Buddhist temple
mom won't like it and that's okay
my dream for this week is not I don't
want to be a religious leader and I don't
want to be a fanatic
we are just friends here we will study deep profound
ideas that will help
you throughout your life and even
after death it will help you
teachers come and go teachers
become
old and teachers change I love you
speak in Chinese but we have many
teachers here and later I want you to
become teachers
so it's good to respect their teachers but don't
respect the teachings too much and then you
will be happy today I am sharing with you and
later maybe you will
share here on this stage
just relax
study these ideas and take it home
use it quietly in
your different countries in your
cultures and you will have a happy life
usually we start with meditation in the morning
because you are still fresh and then
we will have teachings
this is a very famous ancient book my
teacher disappeared and did not teach there
for thirty years
we lived together we are like a
couple who have been married for a long time he was
very kind to me and he taught this book
me three times very slowly
each time it took 10 years and he
teaches very slowly every word
so enjoy the only
good thing McDonald's and KFC
meat is not good for you
they kill 10 billion chickens every year
don't eat it but
french fries are good and don't eat
fast
enjoy these teachings I started
teaching this book 8 years ago we
went through half of the book I chew the teaching
potatoes like french fries so
enjoy just enjoy
well and have fun it's very important when you
come to such teachings to
go swimming in the pool or in the sea there is
too much sleep a lot not for the class
but have fun we are on vacation for free
and it is also very important to rest so
we will have fun together
I teach you meditation okay jasmine
yes children can go
children can go to a special place for
children
I would like to thank dad teaches
welcome teacher for children Bernie
from Canada he has
many years of experience he also
completed a three-year silent retreat
in one small room so he is a
great teacher he has a lot of experience in
teaching Chinese children to Chinese
children, so we are glad that he is here
with us, so there is a special meditation I have been
teaching it for two or three years,
we started this meditation in Mexico,
or maybe a Mexican group, stand up
[applause]
they all became teachers, they completed the
18th say courses, the 18th, 7 courses,
and now they teach and the SEO course, and I
hope that you will also learn to do this,
but we started this, I remember that this is a
meditation, we started doing it in Mexico,
specifically, let me tell you the
story of this meditation, I already told you
last time, but the story begins
with Na Sanghi, he lived
1700 years ago, his books are very famous
in China,
especially the collection of Mahayana books, Pomakhai,
and many of his books were translated with
Fountain,
mainly this is the Maidan school, so I
think that his books are mainly known in
some province of China, these are very
good books, and posture met Maitreya of
the future, I will be, and he studied these teachings with him,
had taught him this
meditation, it is very famous, this
meditation should be very good for
understanding  your future lives so
we will work on this work with this
meditation 5 parts usual razor during the
retreat I do one part
we go through one part but it seems to me you are
ready to go through all five parts it
takes a little more time and
therefore every day we will add
one part
let's do it so ready
sometimes when I teach meditation
some people quickly immediately sit down
on the floor we walked we meditate
we need to sit like this
I say why will I always sit like this on the
floor of the
game you don't know don't understand why he
sat like this 2000 years ago there were no chairs
just like that sitting to meditate on
chairs is normal you can meditate on a
chair
I have an official
meditation cushion dance dance 2 from the Stanley company
but I put them on my sofa this is a
pillow so it is more comfortable so you
can sit on a chair and sit straight
legs and feet on the floor do not clamp your
legs when sitting on the table on the table
sit straight when we meditate in a group it is
very important that it is quiet it helps
other people and I will say always
turn off your phone before meditation
and it is better to clear it now  throat before
meditation, don't cough anymore, and
how to fold your hands, you have a choice, if it's
a little cold for you here, then you
put your left hand in the first and
second from the top, your right hand in all
images of Buddha, it's depicted like this,
but if you sit like this, in
fact, it distracts you in meditation
because you kind of squeeze your fingers,
auto-save them, I like it
just relaxed like this, and
or if, for example, the room is too
warm for you, then you can fold your
hands like this on 2 knees, you have three choices, you
can do it like this, like this, fingers
down, I like an intermediate
state like this, then they hurt, these ones,
I also went through a three-year
silent retreat from 2000 to 2003,
stayed in one room for three years without
talking, I tried everything,
I found the right pose, the right pose
for meditation, the one that suits you,
everyone is different, everyone has different bodies, so
try different options and choose what is more
comfortable for you, my body, your body,
different bodies, for example, Keisha Michael, I won't put it
away, I need a network, differently, maybe
your peak is medium-sized, then on
what you are sitting maybe you generous peak
everyone is different so sit as it is
comfortable for you try try different
positions and see what is comfortable for you
and no matter how you fold your fingers it is
good for the thumb and
index fingers to touch each
other then the pro will
travel here and circulate the chepra it
will circulate throughout the body
you can try it almost touches
but not quite you will also feel
how prana or energy circulates in
general try and so the
face is relaxed
[music]
usually when I meditate my shoulders start to
freeze and I need to be attentive
to relax my shoulders many
meditation teachers tell me that my
shoulders are too tense the mouth is relaxed a
small smile will help your pro not to
move throughout the body
the stomach is slightly pulled inward the
forehead is relaxed
the eyes are relaxed
[music]
and now we will study meditation dance 2 and
today we will go through one part
usually in this meditation we begin by
observing our breathing
but in the lion dance we do not start with
breathing we start with the external sound in the
room and in this  in the room we have
for example a small sound of the air conditioner
focus on these sounds put
your mind on this sound
when in the evening we go to bed we put
our head on the pillow and in the dance
you put your mind on the sound just like you
put your head on the pillow let's
try just listen to the sound and we
begin to concentrate
now we will go deeper
and try to hear the beating of your
heart
put your mind on the sound of the heartbeat
now let's dive inside the heart
and our heart is like a small
small apartment
imagine that you are inside this heart the
walls of the heart beat around you
and this is not a dark
damp place it is very elegant and
small apartments
sunlight comes through the windows it
feels like a very beautiful open
space and so let's dive into
our heart and enjoy this even
quieter place
we will meditate for many days
and the pron will increase and sometimes it
increases too much there is therefore a
special way how to make sure that the pron does not
increase too much
I want you to learn this right
now because we will meditate for many days
when you exhale
at the end of the breath the lungs stop
at  There is still a little air left
in the lungs and it will increase,
adjust, and you will have too much
energy and you will start to
feel nervous, so there is a
special method that can be used
when you exhale,
when you are finished, exhale, then
exhale a little more,
that is, the exhalation becomes such a long
exhalation, then a short pause
and another short exhalation. If you are very
aware of your exhalation and you do
this special method, then
you will not be nervous or feel
any tension. Let's try 56
breaths. When you exhale, at the end of the
exhalation, exhale a
little more. Before this, it was a normal exhalation.
Let's try together. When the
exhalation ends, then exhale a
little more.
Let's go back to the apartment in the
house.
Now imagine that these apartments are
inside your heart a little more. I
like to imagine a large penthouse
on the top floor of a tall building. There are
many rooms.
I am in a room that is in the very
center. I meditate there. It is still
cleansed. A lot of sunlight. Well, the sound of the
walls that are hitting is already felt
a little further away and here it is even quieter
and now  here in this small meditation room
next to me there is a small table and
on the table there is a small sugar bowl
I open the lid of this sugar bowl and
put my finger inside the sugar and when I
take my finger out small
sugar crystals remain on my finger I want the
meditation to be deeper and even
more powerful so I decide to place
my mind inside this sugar crystal
so my mind becomes smaller and
smaller and smaller and a small window
opens in this sugar crystal
it penetrates through the window inside this
crystal
very small like the tip of a needle and
when I get inside this sugar crystal
I am very surprised that inside there is a very
beautiful room
very rich beautiful wood inside there are
many beautiful pillows and soft
sunlight penetrates inside the
ideal room for meditation and I
remain in this very quiet place
enjoy
now I would like to open my mind
a little because this small
sugar crystal can be felt
a little
cramped
so my my mind becomes the water of the
Pacific Ocean and spreads to the edges of
this world
some shores touch Thailand
some touch China
other shores touch California a
very, very big ocean  wide and
very quiet and very deep imagine
your mind
that is still inside a
sugar crystal
but as big as the Pacific Ocean
and calm and deep
now I want my mind to become even
bigger I expand my mind to the sky
beyond the ocean so my mind
extends to all the water of the ocean and the
other half of my mind
extends to all the blue sky above the
ocean very big open
very quiet and the space is very
relaxed
three deep exhalations
let's
not forget to exhale a little more after
you finish a normal exhalation
and slowly open your eyes I
like to stretch
eat very well now drink
something guys I will need a
microphone for questions it is
important for you to be warm in the room we have
people from all different countries here some
like cold rooms
some like people like it to be warm
in the room we will make the room
a little colder please
bring a shawl with you
because otherwise you can get sick under the
air conditioning
so please bring a shawl in about
ten minutes we will take a break
for pee break you can
if you have any questions about
your meditation maybe this meditation
or any meditation that you
do if you want to ask a question
please raise your hand we have a
microphone
She said thank you very much. The teacher
says please. I want to know what the
general
advantage is. Why are you? What is the
benefit of this meditation? This
meditation has 2 parts, 9 steps.
We will go through all 9 steps. What is the
first step? Yes,
air conditioning, we don't count it as step
number zero. True, air conditioning is the first
step, but this is not meditation. We also just
listen to the sound of the air conditioner.
After the air conditioner, what step is the heart? This is
step 1. The first step is the next step. We
dive inside the heart. This is the second step.
What is the third step?
Yes, you place it inside in the middle.
The heart is inside.
The fourth step is what is the sugar crystal.
And the fifth step is the ocean. And you are wrong. 6 is the sky.
We have done 6 parts now. If there are 2 more, there
will be 8. The benefit or advantage of these
eight parts is to simply
calm your mind, make your mind quieter. There is no
other important content in
these parts.
This is not yet the most important meditation.
The purpose of these first five 8 steps is that
you are doing an exercise for your mind.
It's like playing table tennis.
First, you need to warm up, but this is not yet a
game. A warm-up is just warming up.
The first
eight steps are not yet table tennis. This is
just a warm-up. A warm-up for your
mind.
Become  small no become big oh
ocean oh no where deeper dive heart like this this is
like an exercise for the
mind you can scratch your head like this but you
can lose hair if you do this it's
a little dangerous
and step 9 is important and the content is already at
step 9 we will go into the void we will
go to a past life and we will go to a
teacher and this has great
advantages this imitation see
the void
stop death for many people
[music]
will see a past life see the future of
life this is very important in this world all
people think about this life and I can
make money I can get a girl I
can get a donut we are all
interested in this life but it is
good to understand what will happen after that and it is
good to see this and it is good to see where
we came from
what our past life was that is the
purpose of coming to
Thailand
in ordinary life we ​​do not think much about a
past life we ​​do not think much about
future lives and this is normal we
have our own responsibilities we must
take care of children
we must take care of parents and it is
good to focus on this life but it is
also good to prepare yourself for the
future
[music]
if you know  You're leaving in three days. It's a
good idea to start packing your suitcase in advance
today. For example, some of us didn't do that.
I didn't do that. My plane
leaves Shenzhen at 9 a.m.,
and it's 8 a.m. I pack very quickly. I'm in a hurry,
too late, and I even
left my coffee in Shenzhen.
So, it's better if you know what trip you're
going on, what kind of trip is the
next life? It's better to prepare
now. Pack your suitcase three days in advance.
Then you can relax. You won't forget anything. This is the
purpose of
coming here to Thailand. In ordinary life,
usually, and at your ordinary job,
focus on family, work, parents.
When you arrive in
Thailand, pack
your suitcases.
Prepare your suitcases. This is the
time to prepare for
future lives, and this is the main
advantage. Level 9 is where
we will prepare for
future lives. We will try to see
emptiness.
If you see emptiness
correctly, you can throw this suitcase away altogether. There will be
no future lives. You
will become a Buddha.  then you can help everyone
else this is the purpose of 9 9 9 steps
of meditation the first eight steps are
just a warm-up
[music]
if you are going to play table
tennis
like at the Olympics the number is
strange should play table tennis
at nine o'clock the stands are in their
room in the hotel room and getting ready getting ready
and forgot all the reasons the competition is
in Iraq where is Stanley we have a
competition starting and he is still
warming up where
in his room in the hotel he is a stupid guy
call him let him come you see
level 9 this tennis 1 8 steps
warm-up don't stop at the warm-up
it's not tennis yet it's just preparation
some people say I will watch my
breath I will listen to the sound of the air
conditioner
I was serving their hearts for 1 hour 2 hours and
then everyone is done you see they are
warming up but not playing tennis
you see let's take a break
see you in 15 minutes there will be a call I'm
sure
thank you rest and so we will begin we
will begin lam rim
steps on the path this is a very very famous
book the title of the book
gave us long chan us to clutch
us to means freedom freedom  Freedom from
death,
freedom from aging, freedom from suffering, and
freedom for the whole world
and elbows means, for example, if this
freedom and say Stanley,
show me your hand, take it like this, this
means a teacher,
teachers have freedom, not by,
he's like, give me your hand, ready, yes,
take it, this is the name of this book and the film.
If you study this book, then
you will receive not by and you will be able to give to
other people during these 7-8 days,
you have two jobs,
first, accept this not by and keep it,
also study how to do this, learn to give to
other people, you have a special laptop, a
special notebook, a special  A folder with notes,
profit, your manual, and you
can take notes there, write directly
because when you share
this with other people later,
you must have good notes. Don't
be like that famous person
who went to classes for 80 LM
classes, then went home. Life
asks if he studied something. There was
meditation, dance, 2, 9 steps.
Your friend says, oh, really, what's the first
step? 1.
I don't remember well, like the second. Step 2, but
not so important. And the third, what's probably the
ocean? It seems to me like the ocean. Really, no, it's
number five. So, take notes.
Write notes. And when someone
asks you, you can help this
person.
We will also have a special review.
I've been teaching this Lam Rim for 8 years. We will have a
special review. Every day I can
help you review previous
retreats. We will have special
groups for reviewing previous
material. But I'll
repeat one of the materials with you now.
When you go home and people ask
you what you studied, tell me the
nine steps of meditation. He asks you what these
nine steps are. You
will say now. I'll check my notes
now to say for sure. I have
good notes. Cash said.  us
take good notes you can
teach your friends personally
[music]
take notes
go to a coffee shop cafe and share this with
your friends
two things will happen when you
share this knowledge with other people
with your friends all the
waters of the universe will come to see it
if you for example meet at Starbucks
and share knowledge with your
friend this Starbucks will be filled with
people
several will be watching you
and they will be happy like your mom or dad
they will be like oh look she went to Starbucks with her
friends let's go listen
she teaches nine steps good we are
happy
every time
every person when it seems to share with
another person buddhas will come to see
it so don't embarrass me don't
submit the third level for 9 or 5 I
will say Kesha Michael that it
was taught the other way around all the levels so it's
true
every time you share this
knowledge with another person personally it
attracts
but like honey attracts bees the truth is this is
not a story they have power
they feel when someone shares this
knowledge and they will come and look look
she teaches nine steps right
very good
second in  At this moment you are a lama, you are a teacher,
you become a teacher, you are no less a
teacher than Geshe Michael, at this moment the same thing,
if you share
correctly in a cafe,
then you are a real teacher,
don't think that I am a real one, including you are a
real teacher and I will be very happy
and they are there with you, so don't doubt
this. Two things, if you share
correctly according to your notes with others,
first, the
Buddhas will come, look, up to 5, cool, great, I will be
happy, and at this moment you are a
real teacher, a real teacher, as I will be like a
lama,
because the nine steps of this meditation are
real teachings, this is the
true teaching, so please
take good notes, and so let's
go over
where we generally stopped. Nalam Rim,
after 9 years, this is a special book
called steps on the path,
Lam Rim, say lambre lambre, this
means step by step, you don't need to be a
special person, you don't need to be a
monk or a nun,
you can have a family, a good job, you
should have this in your life, your
family life, with your work, for
example, I spent 19 years in the diamond
business while studying for a
Kesha degree, every time I  I went to work,
earned money, helped my family,
helped charity,
studied in parallel in the evenings and on
weekends. So, you must be
responsible, and life is a good job, you
can have a good house, a good car, a
good family.
Take it, you must take on such
responsibility and study Lam Rim.
So, here we are making Lam Rim for you, and you can
do both, you must do
both. A
person who does not take
responsibility for work and family will not take
their responsibility for darma either.
[music]
You see, so it must all be
successful.
In general, darma should make you
smarter. It is supposed to be done darma,
slept smart.
[music]
So, you must have a good job, a
good family,
your children should play the drums. Just kidding.
And so, in Lam Rim, we reached a
special place
and they talk about the problems of this life,
and this means, prepare your suitcase
in advance
for the next life, take care of your
next life, because you will die,
everyone thinks that they will not die. Is it true? Did your
grandmother die before, did your great-great-grandmother? Yes,
this is for Geshe Michael, and your mother is Merlo. Yes,
you will die, no.
we think so in fact it's a line
people it's like a line
mom grandma already left then my grandma
left little mine left now it's my turn don't
think that you are different
we are not different in this book it says the
day will come when the youngest
person in this room will also
die now and no one will remain alive the
person who wrote this book he
said this while he was writing this
book and it became true
all these people have already died the
person who wrote this book is
my teacher's teacher
and we are teachers too there is
no author of the book his student is also not there
his student student his student this is
me this is how it happens
[music] you
can be sad I was walking I don't want to think about it
if your child does something
wrong and then covers his
head with a blanket and he thinks because
I can't see mom mom can't
see me we shouldn't be like this
let's talk about death at home or at
work
don't talk about it too much it's
sad but in Thailand talk about it
constantly because we want to
stop it
they say you can't kill an enemy if you
don't know and two enemies
our enemy is death and we want to kill
this enemy people ask mister  and
eagle, what are you doing? What are you
doing? He says to incense. Yes, I'm a
killer. VDS or a death killer. Death is
afraid of me. I'm going to kill death. This is
our job with you. This is what we study with you
to understand about death. It's
good to study Lam Rim. Don't feel
depressed and fall into depression. We
simply identify who our enemy is
and then we'll shoot you.
We study the problems of life.
6 types of lives. You see animals. You
know animals. This is one type of life. Then
there are people. Then there are hellish creatures. And that's all.
But this doesn't happen. There are no
moves. And I'll
tell you something interesting. It's obvious that I
'll be teaching. I was talking about water.
If you create bad karma, then after
death you'll go to hell.
When I was in school, I was studying.
When I was 17,
the teacher taught us a special
three-month course.
This is a course on an Italian author
called Dante. The author's name is Dante and he
wrote a book called The
Divine Comedy.
This one wrote The Divine Comedy and
there are three parts in this book. Part 1 is all
about water and us.  It took me a whole month to
finish this part, every detail about
A.D.
and this is the same thing that I taught and
[music]
he never went to China this author
but he wrote the same thing he saw hells
so don't tell me that this is
something unusual this does not happen this is the same
information you can read in the classic
books of Europe someone says that this is the
best book ever written
in Europe and there is exactly the same so
it exists
after death you can become an animal
if you are lucky you will become a human but you
can also go to hell 4 choice
animals
there are two kinds of such as superheroes
like iron man and spiderman this is a
small superhero big super
her off superhero
one spiderman the other iron
man and these people really
exist so there are six kinds of
lives and what we want to return to as a
reverse as a human especially we don't
want to go to hell we don't want to be an
animal and there are also hungry ghosts we
don't want to be such a spirit at
least we want to be a human now I'll
tell you something special if you
understand the void well enough then you will get a
guarantee you won't be able to fall down get
Miss in the lower realms after death is like a
contract with Buddha if you understand well enough
about emptiness
then after death you are not me we can
fall down and cannot become an animal you
cannot go to hell and cannot
become a thirsty spirit it is impossible this will be it is
like a guarantee
and the best way to teach this is
with a pen and you have already heard how I
taught this many times there is a famous one once
when I went to Singapore
every year I go to Singapore for ten years
already really 9 we need a pen two pens
every year I teach the pen at the very
beginning on the first day and after I have been
going there for 8 years even in the eighth year
5 5 minutes talking about the pen and after
the lecture a man comes up to me he is not from
Singapore he is from Europe but he does not say
Cash Michael
that it
seems to me you are getting a little old
for some reason you say you repeat all the
time you repeat what I repeat this
pen you and every time it is taught eight
times you have already taught it you have already
forgotten I say no I have not forgotten I
taught you the pen
new they did not use it that's why I  I
have to tell you this again today
why why why
[music]
if you understand well enough what
I'm going to tell you in the next
ten minutes you will not go to hell you will not
become an animal you cannot become a
hungry ghost so this is very important
when you fly home from Shenzhen you
sit next to a
nice guy like Stan Lee on the plane you
can do this he will say where
you are from only engine and where you are flying to Thailand
why did I tell you about my daughter
so share this with other people
why if you share with others
well then in the right way then they will not
go to hell and this is very cool you
will help another person
if a flight attendant asks you for
orange juice or water I
told you about a pen in general you
should always have a pen with you in your pocket
you understand
ready we have a special university in
America the first college mother in America
2 will be in Singapore
[applause]
we teach how to teach a pen
there are 18 parts in teaching a pen 18
points see if you can find them
and so you can sleep during classes after  I don't care
I don't teach after
lunch
but this is a morning class so
focus you can help other
people many lives so teach
learn how to teach two things
when you teach it the first the
second I didn't hear the first should be cool should
be right and should
be fun don't teach like that I
have a friend from Shenzhen she's
always like this don't be so serious life is
very short
our parents can confirm this to us
10 minutes ago they were 20 years old
[music]
wow about me 65 what happened life
will fly by so quickly of
course we had problems in life
everyone has
their own special problems to the noise we can
have a competition on problems went I
can't smile why do I have big
problems do you want to compete on
big problems all which one has
cancer and someone's mother died two days
ago after this class I need to
call this person like that
everyone has problems
[music]
we can be people who we can
be people who have problems who
don't smile or we can  to be people
who have problems but who can
smile, the second is better, there are problems, they
need to be serious and very serious, why are
you smiling, that's better this way, everyone
has problems
[music]
when, therefore, the pen disappears, like this,
be cheerful, and so when
you teach a pen, ask your friend to
give answers,
so I will ask you questions, I
will give an answer, I think it's important to
tell people, just give
natural answers, don't think too
much, this is not a philosophy lesson, a
lesson about a pen, so give me
good answers, what is this
pen, he, look, a little dog, a
sieve, ran up, I'll get up, oh, hello,
show me the dog's boot, the dog's pen, what will the dog do
with the pen, even
grab it with its teeth, does the dog see the pen? No, what does the dog
see the chew toy? Who is
right, the dog or the person, both are right, why
can a dog chew? Enjoy me, you
want, and everything is fine, and then
some stupid person below my
pen, the dog will say, you are such a stupid
person, such a tasty pen, why are you
writing with this, we don't write, we don't write, oh, and
preferably with a toy, below my pen, no, we don't write, oh,
and chew on a toy, everyone is equal
ok now the big question is
if I put a pen here all the people
will leave the room
all the dogs will leave the room no
one will be left in the room at this
moment this pen or chew toy
what is it nothing what do you want it
hurts emptiness
3 this is simplicity and that is castano at
this moment what is it desirable
toy pen not what this emptiness
there are three known wrong ideas about
emptiness I will show you the first idea
emptiness and with
darkness all blackness
emptiness is real no this blackness will not help you black black
black this will not
help you leaves study such emptiness
then you will not be a successful person
you will not have a good family and you
will not be healthy when you are 65 you will be like this it is not just like that
therefore not
black not blackness 2 wrong idea
I am observing the mind
about from right to left it flows do
n't think about anything everything just passes
passes
it is not emptiness someone says don't think
anything what kind of food if you don't think about anything
I will show you on my phone
[music] will I
become this my phone I saw I
just had it  You see, this is the kind of
karma that will happen if you try to
think about nothing, you will always
forget your phone, you see, this is not
emptiness,
here is the 3 famous wrong one,
someone kisses you, someone hits you,
no happiness, no sadness, no, it's
all empty, it's a stupid idea when you
see an image of Buddha, they are not
like this, they are like this,
everyone is smiling, so it's not emptiness,
so what is emptiness? When a dog leaves the
room,
when people leave the room, that
moment, not a pen or a chew
toy, emptiness.
Now, when a person returns
back to the room,
strange things remain there, oh, hello Stanley,
and then I look at this thing and it
changes.
What happens from it becomes what it
becomes a pen. At that moment,
look, what is that emptiness,
emptiness,
pen? It changed. Before that, it was this
something, and now this pen. When, at
what moment, emptiness, emptiness
became a pen. How did it become a pen? It
must be coming from me. Why do
we?
If a dog enters the room, the same
emptiness becomes a pen.
It must be coming from
me. The first pen comes from the person. It
comes to life and the toy happens.  From the dog it also
comes from the pen, then no, no,
what proof
if the pen came from the pen, that
dog would write a letter to its
girlfriend, oh, what a beautiful
tail you have, so the pen must
come from me, a well-known
mistake, some people talk about hanging,
you teach
positive thinking, always be
positive,
everything comes from you, if you want a
diamond, but the secret is yes, I don't want a pen, I want a
diamond, yet it comes from me, and so a
diamond, a diamond, a diamond, you can say the same,
he is Mani Padme, Hum, a diamond, and oil, you
can ask Amitaba, I want a diamond, it
comes from me, Oman, sang along,
anyway, the pen, why does this happen and
from you, but something forces you to see
it as a pen, you have no choice, what
forces you to see in the pen
if you have a seed in your consciousness, 7,
and the pen, when you enter a room, the
seed opens, a small picture
comes out, the picture of the pen comes out of
consciousness and is superimposed 65 times per
second, this is so fast that you
cannot see it, when you meditate a lot,
you can see how the
seeds open, you can see how
these pictures come out,
how often they come out 65 1  A second when
you watch a video online on the internet
if you are in a hotel in Hua
Hin the
internet is not very good
this means that you slow down
the picture there
should be 24 frames per second but if
the internet is not very good the same thing with
your mind
if you meditate a lot you can
see how 7 opens and comes out 65
times a year came out and the internet is 24 per second
and the seeds 65 per second why do you need
additional seeds for smell and taste
and touch your life for it to be
alive the seeds open 65
this opening of seeds is called dependent
origination
everything depends on your seed
origin means that the pen
begins this is real dependent
origination
77 and it turns out what is emptiness
it is here emptiness this is the place for the
picture so that it opens there if the
pen were a pen
from its own country then there would be room for it to
be a chew toy
if I pen is empty
that is there is room for dog seed there is
room for human seed
listen listen listen if you
know how to sow a seed then you can
have everything  What do you want? Why does
your whole life come from seeds?
Everything comes from seeds. My teacher
taught me for about twenty years. Then he
comes to me and says, I taught you
emptiness. Yes, there are seeds. Yes, so
many things come from seeds. So, are
you ready? It means you're ready for your
final exam,
Lama. What is this final exam? Let's
go to New York. Start a business using
seeds and make money. If you do this,
you'll pass the exam.
If you don't, then you haven't studied seeds. It's a
very strange exam, and I did
it. As you know, we had the largest diamond company in the world. We started with three diamonds. We had only three diamonds, and these diamonds were smaller than the sugar crystals you place in your meditation. Well, later we processed more than 300,000 diamonds every day. I had no business experience whatsoever.
Second,
I don't like business at all. I don't have any
experience, and I still don't like business, but this is my
final exam. The exam on seeds.
If a pen comes from seeds, then money
also comes from seeds, and a husband and wife
also come from seeds.
Your body is 60-65 years old, not the body,
and this can be changed.
The meaning of the ladle and 4 I will give you options.
The first is empty, emptiness is black. No.
2 is
emptiness, don't think about anything.
3 is emptiness, no kiss, no blow. Don't be
happy, don't be sad,
be neutral, it's emptiness. No.
4 is the largest diamond
company in the world. A 65-year-old body is like a
25-year-old body. Why does it happen? You
understand. Just learn to sow seeds.
You understand. What's the next step? We must
learn. We are ready. Now I'll put on my
shoes. There are volunteers.
[music]
So
I have a hundred dollars. Forget it. I want to
earn 1,000 dollars.
[music]
Those who receive don't ask. It's
true. I want to sow a seed for 1,000
dollars right now. This is not
a demonstration. This is how Kesha Michael
makes his money. He gets
paid. This is real.
I sow the truth. People ask why
you do this every day. Because I
want money every day. I have to
do it. I have no choice. So I have 100
dollars. I want to teach you how to sow seeds.
Four steps.
You can say  Gersh Slava already
taught this last year I don't care I don't want
you to go to hell I want
you to go to the top if you understand
pen
if you understand 100 dollars you are
protected
if you get into a
car accident when you are in
Bangkok
if you never get home you are
protected understand I have to
do this and I will continue to do this
for the rest of my life four steps to fall how to
sow a seed can you record a video
please record but do
n't post it in HIV from it's
illegal it's wrong I don't care
but there is such a rule so please
protect everyone and so are you ready can
record on your phone
good idea ready so
[music]
[applause]
I'm going home this girl carefully hello
what's your name Evelyn Emily
Amelie
will you help me sow a seed thank you
super
I'm glad we won't help on the networks
there are four steps to sowing seeds don't forget if
you learn this you will easily do
business
you can do ballet when you are 65 you
will have a good family
well study  Four steps, use
four steps, and so the first step is you must
decide what you want today. In my
example, I want to earn $1,000.
My goal today is to earn
$1,000. This is the first step.
Maybe your first step is
much higher. Your goal is much higher. You have a high C. What higher
goal do
I want my husband to wash the dishes every
night? This is a higher goal. Or
maybe I want to be
healthy or I want a beautiful face or I want
peace and
consciousness or I want the whole world to be
happy. You decide. You can sow
any seed,
but today, for demonstration, we have
$77,000 today. The second step is you must
find a partner to sow the seeds.
It is impossible to sow the topic
if you do not use another person.
I hung up. I am too shy and do not want to
talk to other people.
Forget it. You cannot do this. Then
four steps. You can be shy
and be
poor, but you must be a little
strong inside. Go to another
person and reach out to them. You will
help me earn $1,000. Yes,
so just do this. The second step is that
you must have a partner. The third step is that you
need to sow them, like on Emily's network,
please.  Raise your hand like this,
just this hand, one hand, I take 100
dollars, I put it here, I close my
hand and with love, I say 1 2 3 21, sat down,
finished, I sowed the seed,
how is karma, you must understand how the network
karma, you can say, or you can
say, ounces of seeds
karma, seeds, it's the same thing, like in
networks,
you must see yourself doing
what you must hear how you say,
did something good or did something
good, look, I will sow the 7th, does this
sound hit my own ear and
[music]
leaves an imprint
after two hours, this imprint
becomes karma, and this seed will open
and create a pen, or open and create
a thousand dollars
when I put it in my hand, and opening my hand,
this picture hits my eye, and it
touches my mind and creates families,
moment, all the seed of the pool,
thank you, cool, step four, if you don't
know step four, then the seed will be a
pool, but it won't open for
thousands of years, cash, lapal, will receive a thousand
dollars when he carried  It's too late for the old ones,
we don't want to wait a hundred years.
You need to water this seed. You
must. It will fly with the water. The seed will
fly. This is a special meditation. You don't need to
do it like this.
My teacher was in a car
accident before I met him and he
injured his throat. He always
talks like he's from Star Wars. He always yells like this. It's
time for step number four.
What's the name of the game? 4 steps to meditation. The
game. How should I do it? Carry it like that, and goyle.
You taught me not to do it like that, so what should
I do?
I'll show you the special wisdom. There is
such a wisdom. A special mudra
for coffee meditation. Do it like this. Do it
and repeat.
Just don't defeat your neighbor.
Blood and meditation are wise. When to make
coffee? Meditation before you go to
bed. Before you go to bed, why?
Because your mind will then cook
all night while you sleep, and you make
thousands of dollars while you were here.
Your mind will cook all
this time. These are the seeds, so that's how it is.
You must think about the good deeds
you did today. When we  we sleep
and love to think about problems why because
500 people in this room
[music]
think my problem is the most serious Kesha
I know you can smile but you
just don't have my problems my problems are
very serious
when I go to bed it's a special
time to think again and again about my
special problems
my husband is not happy my children are not in
school my boss doesn't love me he
likes another person that's how it is and
all night you will sow bad seeds
don't do that don't worry before
bed the best time to worry
is early in the morning after the
sun has risen sunlight has a special
power and it makes this color makes
big problems small darkness
before bed you are tired this is a bad time to
think about problems
kesha loa could think about her problems
okay I give you permission can what time
can I think about my
problems
my problems in meditation when
make it the best why because
they get smaller
never do in the evening evening
think about
Emily think about her face tonight
Geshe Michael you go to bed only
Michael goes bed I remember Emily's face
big smile she  take your friend
to a restaurant today for a special dinner let's go to
dinner okay take your friends to a special
dinner she looks like this and is so
happy before you go to bed
think about the good things you have
done today what you did well and strongly
I walked that I
did nothing good today
well did something yesterday porridge came out did
nothing good even yesterday
okay 10 years ago did you do anything
good at all in life she yes yes
did well think about it that's also
normal the
seed is there
if you think about the good
things you do the seed will germinate
much faster because it's like
watering it 7 and any good thing
you do
even if 10 years ago I walked even 10 years
ago it was even worse what should I do you
saw that as another person do
something good before Jasmine and the team
work so much in Thailand and it's
incredible be happy about this I will
teach you a special secret Jasmine from with
her team team with her team
Reverend Jigme
they created paradise Amita would for people in  In
Thailand
they created big good seeds.
They worked for a year to prepare everything for
us here. I have good news for you
[music].
Good news. If you
rejoice in what they do, you will
receive 10 percent of it.
Good business, good karmic
business. Don't worry. They won't lose
their 10 percent for them, but they will receive 110,
so just do it. If you don't
remember, can you remember what good you
did for yourself? Think about who did what for others
here. Who else did something
good? You will receive 10 percent. It
seems to me that today 10 percent of the
karma that I created was saved. Jasmine and
her team are together. This is more than
food. I walked and walked. I'm not sure about
teaching. This is quite a large food supply,
and preparing a retreat in Thailand for 500
people is also a large food supply
[music].
Which one should I use? Which coffee should I make?
Meditation? Both? No problem.
Create additional seeds. Okay
[music]. You
can do both.
Now if you understand what I
said today about the pen and seeds,
then you are guaranteed not to get into the problem. Why am I
saying almost? Almost guaranteed.
I'm guaranteed to go deeper
since you came to  Thailand
when you think about the seed creating a
pen you almost get a guarantee if
you die today
which by the way may be true then you will not go
down I was walking why are you saying
almost there is
one kind of emptiness that you must
understand to protect yourself
[music]
this is the last five percent of emptiness
but you must understand this so I will teach
you this now I will tell you never
forget this when you teach emptiness
at Starbucks all the Buddhas are watching you do
n't forget the last five percent these are the
percentages that will really
protect another person here is a real
example
cash this morning you taught us
lion dance meditation and you said
close your eyes and you were looking listen to the sound of the
air conditioner
and then listen to your heart and and
sorry but during meditation
only one thought came to me and it is
donut donut donut donut what's for lunch
I ask my mind to meditate but my mind
doesn't listen to me
I talk to my mind I was walking
now we will meditate
and it says okay then I say Mukesh
Losya said listen to the air conditioner for what he
said listen  heart you can
do this talking to the mind he says yes yes
we will do well let be quiet
think about the heart
core good mind talk to
you well ready let's start donut donut donut donut iota
iota really
wants kidneys paths kidneys packs shut up usa donut donut
you know
you don't think about donuts all day
only when I walked starts meditation
start thinking about donuts why do
you have
in your consciousness seed thinking about
donuts you are not the one who speaks in your mind
listen
what do you always say to your husband what do you
say to your husband dear you can't
speak and listen at the same time
maybe you will stop speaking for at
least 1 minute these trying to
say something it is impossible to speak and listen
at the same time and this is true inside your
own mind you either
speak and or listen and your husband this is
proof that at the same time this
cannot happen either your husband speaks
or your husband serves your mind the same thing
in yours I have the same thing you listen
you can't speak I walked and who is to
talk about  in my mind
who is speaking your moment seeds seeds
seeds say it is not you your seeds
say
there is no you who speaks your idol
your mind is emptiness and seeds
say listen listen
carefully listen protect yourself
after death easily
ask yourself who is speaking in my mind seeds seeds
say my if the one who speaks yours
no one is seeds listen
I am protecting you from hell right now and is there
someone speaking in your mind who
is not a seed no this is that
emptiness that will protect you
now you got protection cool cool
very cool if a pen my hands do
some people nestat if a pen my
hands yes there is is there a
pen in my hand that comes from
my seeds do if I want more pens in
my life how to sow a seed pen you
understand this sowing seeds pens in
my mind
I will do it again is there a pen in my
hand
[music]
[applause]
who creates screaming children comes from
me maybe I need to be more
polite
if a pen my hands do if a pen my
hands that comes from my seeds do
now the big question if a pen in my
hand that does not come from my seeds
no emptiness is emptiness pens and it
half protects  you from hell well we
need a little more ready
can you hear some thoughts in
your mind for 1 minute before
[music]
can you hear in your mind the thoughts
that come from your seeds before
all thoughts come from seeds
[music]
when you listen to your own mind you
listen to the seeds unfolding in your
consciousness the last question is there a
conversation in your mind
that does not come from your media no it is
impossible it is the emptiness of yourself if you
understand this one thing well then you are
protected forever you cannot go to hell it is
impossible cool we are all done and
now
now we can move on to you Rima 20 minutes
total I know you are tired I know you have
traveled a long time and I am very glad that
you came here I think you are very
cool 2 more 20 minutes then we
will take a nice long break I was
also walking already waiting for a break let's
focus on 20 minutes and move on we will
start our book my taught taught
not this book word by word and I want to
do the same for you we will
go word by word slowly and there
will be an advance we enjoy
potatoes  fries and if you eat french
fries too fast you will have
stomach problems it's
lam rim french fries like that
[music]
enjoy don't try to eat it I'm
fast the cat
word by word I was walking it sounds
cool enough that after I die
why be human there is a
rebirth as a superhero
I think I want to try
I can be a little superhero like
spiderman or a big superhero like
iron man
they say that in Hollywood where they make
all these American movies
if you want to make 100 million
dollars make a movie about superheroes they
always make movies movies about superheroes
don't create such sensitive companies
it doesn't bring in money
if you want real money make a
super movie about a superhero why do people like it
I like it myself I don't go to
many movies I always go to movies about
superheroes why are these guys cool
[music]
spiderman is cool when I was a
kid we had this
picture book about spiderman
I ask my mom
mom can I be spiderman when
I grow up can I be  Spider-Man
she says yes and Crimea and how did
Spider-Man become Spider-Man she
says his special spider bit a
radioactive spider
games got it mom every time I see a
spider
bite me bite me a hundred spiders
bit me nothing happened just a lot
itching we all like superheroes and
they exist
that's true that's why
we like these movies
because in the past we were in their place the
reason you like these
movies
is that you remember in a past life you
were like that now you are just people so
it's possible you think for yourself
yes it's cool if I'm lying I would like to
get to this place of superheroes
how powerful and strong these guys are
much more powerful than
Iron Man you know what they do
for fun and I don't know in China you
play some game marbles
we really liked it as a child
when I was six or seven years old
at school they banned this game altogether
because we spent too much time
playing this game after this game and
we call these superheroes maidens
they are just like this game of marbles but
For them, these balls are entire
planets. They play with planets. They blew up a
planet.
They are super powerful. So, it is possible that
some people will think, I want to
become like these superheroes. Play with
planets. It's cool. Now,
the problem is that they have a special
problem in their world.
We call it the world of the so-called "t.f."  This is something we can do. You can get there
if you give them a
lot of money. If you have a lot of money before children, I'm
kidding.
If you do the Dance 2 meditation, the
first eight parts over
and over again without moving on
to the ninth part,
you will sow a special 7 and to become a Virgo, it
sounds cool, really, but there is a problem.
Here in the book it
talks about the problems of these
powerful beings who play with the planets,
the balls, and they have serious problems. We
will study the problems of these TVs, and then
maybe you will decide that you don't want to
be born in such a place. It's better for me to be a
Buddha. Puds help many
more people well, and that's why now
in the book the author talks about the special
problems of these D.F.
[music]
I will pronounce the words from this book to you,
of course, you do not know this language, but this is a
very powerful seed of your moment, it’s like
someone, something very similar, so don’t
worry, don’t say that I was walking, I’m
tired, you are using this ancient language, I have
such a goal, I use it
purposefully, I am trying to sow the seed of
your moment,
okay, so
[music]
very famous words of many people, there are
shawls that you can cover yourself with for warmth,
if you don’t have one, then bring one, bring
shawls with you to keep warm, there are
shawls of different quality, I was in
Ukraine,
who was there with me, Ukrainian friends, I
was at the Premier Palace Hotel
[music]
I went to buy a chance for my friend, an
elderly woman, I don’t know if you know, on the
first floor there is a store, a very
expensive store, a very expensive store, I didn’t know,
I just went inside, I saw a shawl for
my elderly lady, who is
94 years old, I thought that would do, yesterday we
also bought gifts in Shenzhen, I
like to buy gifts for her,
beautiful pink things, red pajamas, I
buy gifts in length,
and that’s in  For example, I bought a carpet, I tell
the girl I want this, and with my foot,
well,
snip-snip-snip-snip, then she burns, 3,000, I
say there is no Ukrainian money, dollars, I
say 33 thousand dollars, I'm like,
maybe some are not so much, and the colors here like, you see,
why are we talking about this?
Listen, if you bring a
shawl for 3,000 dollars in one day,
you use a lot of seeds,
these are very expensive seeds,
you use seeds like three thousand
dollars a day.
If you buy a cheap one for 100 dollars, it's
not so convenient, but a cheaper seed
[music]
only used a 100-dollar 7 and I'm
not teaching you to buy cheap clothes, I'm
not teaching you this. I think you
should buy beautiful clothes and
buy for other people, I can
always have enough seeds for you to
have beautiful clothes always, so all the
husbands who are here when I understand you're going home
with your wife, she'll see something
beautiful in the States at the airport, you're not allowed to
say
Kesha, Michael said that you can't buy an
expensive shawl, don't talk about your wife
Keshi Michael said that you should
only wear cheap clothes I didn't
say that I said a husband should buy the
most beautiful clothes for his wife this is a very
good seed
[music]
but these virgins
they burn a
huge amount of good seeds when
they play one game of marbles with the
planets they use a huge
amount of seeds in that world to
stay there during that day very
very expensive very this karma very
expensive food what is happening the
big lama says your job in this
life is not to use all the seeds
but to earn seeds your seeds
work it doesn't have the most expensive car
or the most expensive house or the most expensive
shoes you are not a consumer of karma you should
be a producer of karma you have a
choice in your life you can
be a person who uses more
seeds or you can be a person
who creates more of yourself you understand and
our job as
Buddhists is to create more seeds not to
use more seeds
but to create I didn't say never
buy a Tesla I didn't say
that I didn't say that I
said don't use more seeds than
you create buy a Tesla and take
other people away constantly
when you create more
Tesla seeds than you spend Tesla seeds
Buy beautiful clothes, go
with a friend to Starbucks and give them some
grass, there will be 100, there will be
an observer at this Starbucks next to you, she
teaches the pen correctly, she teaches it
cool
and also looks beautiful, cool, then you
create a new seed,
you make me happy,
so go ahead, buy beautiful clothes,
wear beautiful clothes when they teach
the pen, but create more seeds than you
use,
I went how to create more seeds than you
use, 7, and this is mental,
and I teach my friends' pens to
Starbucks today,
you should tell your husband, sorry, I have to
teach my pens today in a cafe,
so in the morning it's okay if I buy a new
dress, your husband will say, why is this not for
me? I'm going to Starbucks, I teach the pen,
everyone will be there, I need to look
beautiful, good, and if you have such
motivation, that's true, in fact, this is
not a joke, if you have such motivation, then
you will sow more good seeds than the
seeds that you spend buying a
beautiful dress, this is smart shopping
[applause]
family asks, I went this year to
Germany, where are all the Germans? I
wanted to say yes, Fedor, loan for Kutum,
orgy in a guest house,
I'm level 10, I submitted to Germany for the first time,
10, that's right, I always teach
new levels of Germany for the first time, because
Sylvia started level 10 in Germany 10 years
ago
[music]
[applause]
and she's published more of my books than
anyone else,
any other country, she publishes more books
than any other country,
thank you
10 80,
how not to get angry when we teach
in China or Singapore,
come, you have to come, and many people
ask me, I was going, what will level 11 be about,
it's always a secret, and people are like, what is it,
what will be on level 11, what will be on
level 1, I'll tell you, but don't tell
anyone, advanced
shopping
[music]
[applause]
how to shop, how to shop,
while creating more seeds than you
spend on, if you buy a new
shirt for Lam Rim class, and you  So,
how much does this cost? How many seeds will I burn?
For three hours, because I have our new
shirt, I should earn more seeds
than this amount. What do you
mean? I taught for three hours.
Because I teach, the Buddha's pen should
come.
[music]
Because I protect 500 people from
going to hell, the Buddhas are obliged to come there.
I should wear a nice shirt. If I
think so, I will create more good seeds
than the seeds I waste. I didn't
say
I went. I didn't say never buy
expensive clothes.
Where did I go? I said, that is, the seeds
you waste always plant a
larger quantity. Now, what's the problem
with these beings in the realm of devas? They don't
understand the pen. They just use
their seeds and
waste them. Every deva who
dies in this realm
immediately goes to hell. Why did they
use up all the good seeds and
didn't create new ones? Cool, thank you. We'll
stop for today.